email:JoshAVilla1989@gmail.com

315 222-3474 / 352 449-8588

SUMMARY

Military veteran extensively trained in weapons, small unit tactics, and Reconnaissance/Surveillance /Target Acquisition. Detail oriented and maintained composure under pressure. Highly effective in the area of verbal communications. Proven effective leader in the areas of intelligence gathering techniques, emergency response, firearms safety, and defensive tactics. Small arms weapons specialist. Experienced in leading diverse groups of individuals in a combat environment. Routinely worked autonomously for extended periods of time without supervision.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Attention to Detail
- Creative Problem Solver
- Cultural and Global Competence
- Independant
- Critical Thinker
- Team Player

EXPERIENCE

United States Army, Forward Observer, Ft. Wainwright AK, Ft. Drum NY 2007-2015

- Hand picked by the Battalion Commander to lead and direct his Personal Security Detachment (PSD) of 5 soldiers while conducting combat operations in Afghanistan.
- Led and directed the Personal Security Detachment (PSD) of 12 soldiers for the company commander while conducting combat operations in Afghanistan.
- Personally conducted small arms training of 300 Afghan National Police.
- Evaluated 5-7 subordinate soldiers on monthly performance.
- Maintained expert qualification on all assigned weapons.
- Conducted pre-deployment training at the National Training Center in California, and the Joint Readiness Training Center in Louisiana, which required full integration of all tactics and training to receive a deployable status.
- Attained a 100% pass rate on all quarterly evaluations in accordance with all regulations.
- Three combat tours (Iraq 2008-2009, Afghanistan 2011-2012, Afghanistan 2013-2014).
- Directed supporting fire to suppress enemy fire and allow troops to maneuver the area.
- Coordinated operations with artillery and air support units.

EDUCATION

- GED (Glendale Community College, Glendale, AZ)
- U.S.Army Basic Training (Ft Sill, OK)
- U.S. Army Advanced Individual Training, Fire Support Specialist, (Ft Sill, OK)
- U.S. Army Combat Life Saver Course (Ft Wainwright, AK)
- U.S. Army Joint Fires Observer (Ft Wainwright, AK)
- U.S. Army Non-Commissioned Officer Professional Development Course (Ft Drum, NY)

JOSHUA A. VILLA PAGE 2

AWARDS

- Army Commendation Medal (2)
- Army Good Conduct Medal (2)
- National Defense Service Medal
- Iraq Campaign Medal (2)
- Afghanistan Campaign Medal (2)
- Global War on Terror Service Medal
- Combat Action Badge (CAB)
- Overseas Service Ribbon (2)
- Non-Commissioned Officer Professional Development Ribbon